<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!--<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
]>-->
<!---?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>-->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-tsvwg-careful-resume-06"
     ipr="trust200902">
    <!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
    ipr values: full3667, noModification3667, noDerivatives3667
    you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN"
    they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->

    <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

  <front>
    <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header
     - it is only necessary if the
full title is longer than 39 characters -->

    <title abbrev=" Congestion Control Convergence"> Convergence of Congestion
    Control from Retained State</title>

    <author fullname="Nicolas Kuhn" initials="N" surname="Kuhn">
      <organization>Thales Alenia Space</organization>
      <address>
        <email>nicolas.kuhn.ietf@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Emile Stephan" initials="E" surname="Stephan">
      <organization>Orange</organization>
      <address>
        <email>emile.stephan@orange.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Godred Fairhurst" initials="G" surname="Fairhurst">
      <organization>University of Aberdeen</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Department of Engineering</street>
          <street>Fraser Noble Building</street>
          <city>Aberdeen</city>
          <code>AB24 3UE</code>
          <country>UK</country>
        </postal>

        <email>gorry@erg.abdn.ac.uk</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Raffaello Secchi" initials="R" surname="Secchi">
      <organization>University of Aberdeen</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Department of Engineering</street>
          <street>Fraser Noble Building</street>
          <city>Aberdeen</city>
          <code>AB24 3UE</code>
          <country>UK</country>
        </postal>

        <email>r.secchi@erg.abdn.ac.uk</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Christian Huitema" initials="C" surname="Huitema">
      <organization>Private Octopus Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <email>huitema@huitema.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2023" />

    <!-- If the month and year are both specified and are the current ones, xml2rfc will fill
in the current day for you. If only the current year is specified, xml2rfc will fill
in the current day and month for you. If the year is not the current one, it is
necessary to specify at least a month (xml2rfc assumes day="1" if not specified for the
purpose of calculating the expiry date).  With drafts it is normally sufficient to
specify just the year. -->

    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

    <area>Transport</area>

    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

     <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc,
     IETF is fine for individual submissions.
     If this element is not present, the default is "Network Working Group",
     which is used by the RFC Editor as a nod to the history of the IETF. -->

     <keyword>Transport, Congestion Control, QUIC</keyword>

    <!-- Keywords will be incorporated into HTML output
     files in a meta tag but they have no effect on text or nroff
     output. If you submit your draft to the RFC Editor, the
     keywords will be used for the search engine. -->

    <abstract>
      <t>This document specifies a cautious method for IETF transports that
      enables fast startup of congestion control for a wide
      range of connections.
      It reuses a set of computed congestion control parameters that
      are based on previously observed path characteristics between
      the same pair of transport endpoints. These parameters
      are stored, allowing them to be later used to modify the congestion control behavior
          of a subsequent connection.</t>
      <t>It describes assumptions
      and defines requirements for how a
      sender utilizes these parameters to provide opportunities for a
      connection to more rapidly get up to speed and rapidly utilize available
      capacity. It discusses how use of the method impacts the capacity at a
      shared network bottleneck and the safe response that is needed after any
      indication that the new rate is inappropriate.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

<middle>
<section anchor="sec:introduction" title="Introduction">
    <t>All Internet transports are required to either
    use a Congestion Control (CC) method, or
    to constrain their rate of transmission <xref target="RFC8085"></xref>. In 2010,
    a survey of alternative CC methods <xref target="RFC5783"></xref>, noted that there
    are challenges when a CC method operates across an Internet path with a high and/or
    varying Bandwidth-Delay Product (BDP). This mechanism targets a
    solution for these challenges.</t>

    <t>A CC method typically takes time to ramp-up the sending rate,
    called the "slow-start phase", informally known as the time to "Get up
    to speed". This slow-start phase defines a time in which a sender
    intentionally uses less capacity than might be available, with the
    intention to avoid or limit overshooting the available capacity for the path.
    The slow-start design can increase queuing (latency or jitter) and/or
    congestion packet loss for the flow. Any overshoot can have a
    detrimental effect on other flows sharing a common bottleneck. 
    A sender can use a method to observe the rated of acknowledged data,
    and seek to avoid overshooting the bottleneck capacity (e.g., Hystart++
    <xref target="RFC9406"></xref>).
    In the extreme case, an overshoot can result in persistent congestion
    with unwanted starvation of
    other flows <xref target="RFC8867"></xref> (i.e., preventing other flows
    from successfully sharing the capacity at a common bottleneck).</t>

    <t>This document proposes a CC method that is expected to
     reduce the time to complete a transfer
    when the transfer sends significantly more data than allowed by the
    Initial congestion Window (IW), and
    where the BDP of the path is also significantly
    more than the IW.
    It introduces an alternative method to select initial CC parameters,
    that seek to more rapidly and safely grow the sending rate controlled by
    then congestion window (CWND). CC methods that are rate-based can make
    similar adjustments to their target sending rate.</t>
     
    <t>This method is based on temporal sharing (sometimes known as
    caching) of a saved set of CC parameters that relate to previous observations
    of the same path. The parameters include:
    the saved_cwnd for the path and the minimum Round Trip Time (RTT). These
    parameters are stored and used to modify the CC
    behavior of a subsequent connection between the
    same endpoints.</t>

    <t>When used with the QUIC transport, this provides transport services that resemble
    those currently available in TCP, using methods such as TCP Control Block (TCB)
    <xref target="RFC9040"></xref> caching.</t>

    <section anchor="CC-params" title="Use of saved CC parameters by a Sender">
        <t>CC parameters are used by Careful Resume for three functions:
        <list style="numbers">
            <t>Information about the utilised path capacity (saved_cwnd) to
            determine an appropriate set of CC parameters for re-using the path.</t>
            <t>Information to characterize the saved path to
            confirm whether the current path
            is consistent with a saved path.</t>
	    <t>Information to check the validity of the saved CC parameters, including
	    the time for which the parameters remain valid.</t>
        </list></t>
           
            <t>"Generally, implementations are advised
            to be cautious when using saved CC parameters on a new path",
            as stated in <xref target="RFC9000"></xref>.
            While this statement has been proposed in the context of QUIC standardization, this advice is appropriate for any IETF transport protocol.
            Care is therefore needed
            to assure safe use and to be robust to changes
            in traffic patterns, network routing, and link/node conditions.
            There are cases where using the saved parameters of a previous
            connection is not appropriate (e.g., <xref target="rec-phase"></xref>).</t>
    </section>  <!-- End of use with care -->
          
    <section anchor="rec-choice" title="Receiver Preference">
            <t>Whilst a sender could take optimization decisions without considering
            the receiver's preference, there are cases where a receiver
            could have information that
            is not available at the sender, or might benefit from
            understanding that Careful Resume might be used.
            In these cases, a receiver
            could explicitly ask to enable or inhibit tuning of the CC
            when an application initiates a new session or resume an
            existing one.
            A receiver could also tune policies for using the connection
            (e.g., managing the
            receiver window or flow credit).</t>
	    
            <t> Examples where a receiver might request not to use Careful Resume include:
            <list style="numbers">
                <t>a receiver that can predict the pattern of traffic
                (e.g., insight into the volume of data to be sent,
                the expected length of a session, or the required maximum transfer rate);</t>
                <t>a receiver with a local indication that a path/local
                interface has changed since the CC parameters were stored;</t>
                <t>knowledge of the current hardware limitations at a receiver;</t>
                <t>a receiver that can predict additional capacity will be needed
                for other concurrent or later flows
                (i.e., prefers to activate Careful Resume for a different connection).</t>
        </list></t>

            <!--QUIC introduces the concept of transport parameters (Section 4 of
                <xref target="RFC9000">). -->
            <t>A related document proposes an extension for QUIC that allows
            sender-generated CC parameters to be stored at the receiver
            <xref target="I-D.kuhn-quic-bdpframe-extension"></xref>.
            Transferring the information to a receiver releases the need for a
            sender to retain transport state for each
            receiver, and allows a receiver to express a preference for whether
            to use the method.</t>
    </section> <!-- End of Receiver Preference -->

    <section anchor="sec-use_case" title="Examples of Scenarios of Interest">

        <t> This section provides a set of examples where Careful Resume is expected to improve performance.</t>

        <t>Either endpoint can assume the role of a
        sender or a receiver. Careful Resume also supports a
        bidirectional data transfer,
        where both endpoints simultaneously send data
        (e.g., remote execution of an application, or a
        bidirectional video conference call).</t>

        <t>In one example, an application uses a series of connections over a path
        (i.e., resumes a connection to the same endpoint).
        Without a new method,
        each connection would need to individually
        discover appropriate CC parameters, whereas Careful Resume allows the flow
        to use a rate that is based on the previously observed CC parameters.</t>

        <t>In another example, an application connects after a disruption
        had temporarily reduced the path
        capacity. When the endpoint
        returns to use a path with the original characteristics, using
        a rate that is based on the previously observed CC parameters.</t>
        <t>
        There is particular benefit for
        any path with an RTT that is much larger than typical
        Internet paths.
        In a specific example, an application connected via a satellite access network
        <xref target="IJSCN"></xref>
        could require 9 seconds to complete a 5.3 MB transfer
        using standard CC, whereas a sender using Careful Resume
        could be reduce this transfer time to 4 seconds. The time to complete a 1 MB transfer could
        similarly be reduced by 62 % <xref target="MAPRG111"></xref>. This benefit is also
        expected for other sizes of transfer and for different path
        characteristics when a path has a large BDP.</t>

        <t>{XXX-Editor note: A future revision would helpfully provide further Path Examples here.}</t>
    </section> <!-- Introduction: End of examples -->
   
</section> <!-- End of introduction and motivation -->

<!-- ****************************************************************************************** -->
<!-- The protocol spec follows below here, examples later -->
<!-- ****************************************************************************************** -->

<section anchor="notation" title="Language, Notation and Terms">

    <t>This subsection provides a brief summary of key terms and the
    requirements language.</t>

    <section anchor="sec:req_language" title="Requirements Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
         "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
         "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in
         BCP 14
         <xref target="RFC2119"/>
         <xref target="RFC8174"/>
         when, and only when, they appear in all
         capitals, as shown here.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sec-terms_def" title="Notation and Terms">
        <t> The document uses language drawn
        from a range of IETF RFCs.  It defines current, and saved values for a set of CC
        parameters:
        <list>

            <!-- GF (Feb 2023): Removed the IW from this information block??? -->
            <!-- it could potentially be in the BDP Frame ID, but is not needed here -->
            <!--    <t>IW: Initial Window <xref target="RFC9002"></xref>;</t> -->

	    <t>CC parameters: A set of saved congestion control parameters from
	    a previously observed connection (see <xref target="CC-params"/>).</t>
        
        <t>Careful Resume (CR): The method specified in this document to select
        initial CC parameters, that seeks to more rapidly and safely
        increase the initial sending rate.</t>
		
	    <t>current_endpoint_token: The Endpoint Token of the current receiver;</t>
	     
	    <t>current_rtt: A sample measurement of the current RTT;</t>

	    <t>endpoint_token: An Endpoint Token identifying a path to a receiver;</t>

	    <t>flight_size: The currently unacknowledged volume of data sent by the CC method;</t>

	    <t>jump_cwnd: The resumed CWND, used in the Unvalidated Phase.</t>

	    <t>LifeTime: The time for which the saved CC parameters can be safely re-used.</t>

	    <t>max_jump : The maximum configured jump_cwnd;</t>

		<!--- XXX RS to check -->
	    <t>PipeSize: A measure of the validated available capacity based on the acknowledged data;</t>

            <t>saved_cwnd: A value of CWND derived from observation of a
            previous connection, which reflects capacity
            that was utilised by the observed connection;</t>

	    <t>saved_endpoint_token: The Endpoint Token of a previous connection to a
            receiver;</t>

            <t>saved_rtt: The preserved minimum RTT, e.g., corresponding to the minimum
            of a set RTT of measurements over the last 5 minutes of a connection.</t>
 
        </list>
        </t>

        <t>The Endpoint Token is described in <xref target="endpoint_token"></xref>.
        </t>

    </section> <!-- End of Notation: End of terms -->
</section><!-- End of Notation -->

<section anchor="sec-phase" title="The Phases of CC using  Resume">
    <t>This section defines a series of phases that the
    CC algorithm moves through as a connection
    uses Careful Resume, as shown in Figure 1.</t>

   <t>
 <artwork align="left" name="" type="" alt=""><![CDATA[
     
Observe ...> Connect -> Reconnaissance --------------------> Normal
(Normal)                 |                                    ^
                         v                                    |
                        Unvalidated --> Validating -----------+
                         |               |                    |
                         |               |                    |
                         +---------------+--> Safe Retreat ---+
     
 ]]></artwork>
</t>
	
<t> Figure 1: Phases when a connection uses the Careful Resume. The Observe Phase
is performed by an established connection as an action within the Normal Phase. 
Examples of the transitions between phases are provided in <xref target="Examples"></xref>.</t>
     
    <!-- These subsections to match next section format -->
	
    <section title="Observe Phase">
        <t>During a previous established connection, the CC parameters for the specific path
        to an endpoint are saved. This characterizes the path and
        determines the saved_cwnd.
	The saved_cwnd is a measure of the currently utilised capacity for the connection,
	measured as the number of bytes sent over a RTT. This could be computed
	by measuring the volume of data acknowledged in one RTT.
        The CC parameters also include the minimum RTT
        (saved_rtt) and the receiver
        Endpoint Token (saved_endpoint_token).</t> 
	<t>An implementation
        can store the CC parameters at the server (or could exchange this information
        with a receiver <xref target="I-D.kuhn-quic-bdpframe-extension"></xref>).</t>
	    
        <t><list style="symbols">
	 <t>Observe Phase: The sender updates the stored CC parameters
            and/or sends the updated CC parameter
            information for the saved_cwnd
            after each observation.</t>
		
	  <t>Observe Phase (Small CWND): If the measured CWND is less than four times the Initial Window (IW)
            (i.e., CWND less than IW*4),
            a sender SHOULD NOT store and/or send CC parameters. The additional actions associated with
	    performing Careful Resume for a small CWND would not justify the use of the method.</t>

          <!-- The requirement below really applies to BDP Frame if adopted, otherwise needs explained -->
          <t>Observe Phase (Sending CC Parameters): When sending the CC parameters to a receiver,
	    these ought to be updated
            if there are significant changes in the saved CC parameters;
            The frequency of update SHOULD be less than
            one update for several RTTs <xref target="I-D.kuhn-quic-bdpframe-extension"></xref>.</t>
    </list></t>

            <t>Implementation notes are provided in <xref target="req-observe"></xref>.</t>

    </section> <!-- End of define Observe Phase:-->
          
    <section anchor="rec-phase" title="Reconnaissance Phase">
	<!--- XXX RS Check -->
        <t> A sender enters the Reconnaissance Phase after connection setup.
        In this phase, the CWND is initialised to the IW, and the sender transmits initial data.
        The CWND MAY be increased using normal CC as each acknowledgment
	confirms delivery of a packet (i.e., the CC is unchanged).</t>

        <t>The phase seeks to determine if the path is consistent with
        a previously observed path (saved in the CC parameters).
	There are a set of conditions that need to be confirmed before the sender is
        permitted to enter the Unvalidated Phase:

        <list style="symbols"> <!-- list of phase -->

            <t>Reconnaissance Phase (Endpoint change):
            If the current remote endpoint is not the same as a saved endpoint,
            the sender MUST enter the Normal Phase. If the Endpoint Token differs
            (i.e., the saved_endpoint_token is different from the
            current_endpoint_token), it is assumed to represent a different network path.
            The sender also enters the Normal Phase when there are no corresponding saved CC parameters.</t>

	    <t>Reconnaissance Phase (Lifetime of saved CC parameters): The CC parameters are temporal.
	    If the LifeTime of the observed CC parameters is exceeded <xref target="req-lifetime"></xref>,
	    the CC parameters are no longer used
	    and sender enters the Normal Phase.</t>

             <t>Reconnaissance Phase (Confirming the RTT): During this phase,
             a sender MUST record the minimum RTT for the current connection.</t>  
		
             <t>Reconnaissance Phase (Avoiding using Careful Resume): A receiver can use a method (e.g.,
             <xref target="I-D.kuhn-quic-bdpframe-extension"></xref>) to request
             that the sender instead enters the Normal Phase.</t>

	     <t> {XXX-Editor note: Reconnaissance Phase (Is there a need for a minimum
	     required number of RTT samples to confirm a path ???? }</t>
		
            <t>Reconnaissance Phase (Detected congestion): If the sender detects
            congestion (e.g., packet loss or ECN-CE marking), the sender does not use the Careful
	    Resume method and MUST enter the Normal Phase to respond to the detected congestion.
	    </t>

            <t>Reconnaissance Phase (Using saved_cwnd):
            Only one connection can use a specific set of saved CC parameters.
            If another connection has already started to use the saved_cwnd, the sender
            MUST enter the Normal Phase.</t>

            <t>Reconnaissance Phase (Rate-limited sender):
            If the sender is rate-limited <xref target="RFC7661"></xref>, 
	    it might send insufficient data
            to be able to validate transmission at the higher rate.
            Careful Resume is allowed to remain in the Reconnaissance Phase and to not
            transition to the Unvalidated Phase until the sender
            has more data ready to send in the transmission buffer
            than is permitted by the current CWND.
            In some implementations, the decision to enter the
            Unvalidated Phase could require coordination with the management
            of buffers in the interface to the higher layers.</t>

        </list></t>

        <t>When a sender confirms the path and it
        receives an acknowledgement for the initial data without reported congestion,
        it MAY then enter the Unvalidated Phase.
        This transition occurs when a sender has more data than permitted
        by the current CWND.</t>
        
        <t>When a path is not confirmed, Careful Resume is not used
        and the sender enters the Normal Phase.</t>

        <t>Implementation requirements are provided in <xref target="req-recon"></xref>.</t>

    </section> <!-- End of Reconnaissance Phase -->
     
    <section anchor="unv-phase" title="Unvalidated Phase">
        <t>The Unvalidated Phase is designed to enable the CWND
        to more rapidly get up to speed.
	</t>
	    
       <t>The sender only enters this phase when the saved CC parameters are
	confirmed:</t>

	<t><list> <t>Unvalidated Phase (Confirming the path on entry): The calculation
	     of a sending rate from a saved_cwnd
             is directly impacted by the RTT, therefore a significant change in the RTT
             is a strong indication that the previously observed CC
             parameters may not be valid for the current path.
             If the RTT measurement is
	     not confirmed, i.e., 
	     the current_rtt is greater than or equal to
             (saved_rtt / 2) and the current_rtt is less than or equal to (saved_rtt x 10)
	     <xref target="sec-confirm-rtt"></xref>),
	     the sender MUST enter the Normal Phase.</t>
	</list></t>
	    
        <t>When the RTT is confirmed:</t>
        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Unvalidated Phase (Initialising PipeSize): The variable PipeSize if initialised to CWND on
                entry to the Unvalidated Phase. This records the
                value before the jump is applied.</t>
            
             <t>Unvalidated Phase (Setting the jump_cwnd):
             To avoid starving other flows that could have either started
             or increased their used capacity after the Observation Phase,
             the jump_cwnd MUST be no more than half of the saved_cwnd.
             Hence, jump_cwnd is less than  or equal to the (saved_cwnd/2). CWND = jump_cwnd. </t>
             
             <t>Unvalidated Phase (Pacing tranmission): Transmission using an unvalidated
             CWND MUST use pacing.</t>
             
             <t>Unvalidated Phase (Confirming the path during tranmssion)
             If a sender determines that the previous CC parameters
             are not valid (due to a detected path change),
             the Safe Retreat Phase is entered.
	     (The sender has not yet received feedback for the jump in CWND, because
	     less than an RTT has passed before the Unvalidated Phase was entered.
	     Therefore, any detected congestion must have resulted from packets sent
             before the Unvalidated Phase.)</t>
             
             <t>Unvalidated Phase (Receiving acknowledgements for reconnaisance packets):
                 The variable PipeSize if increased by the amount of data that is acknowledged
                 by each acknowledgment (in bytes). This indicated a previously unvalidated packet has been
                 succesfuly sent over the path.</t>

             <t>Unvalidated Phase (Receiving acknowledgements for an unvalidated packet):
	     The sender enters the Validating Phase when the first acknowledgement is
             received for the first packet number (or higher) that was sent in the Unvalidated Phase.</t>
        </list></t> <!-- End of list of actions -->

        <t>Implementation notes are provided in <xref target="req-unvalid"></xref>. </t>
    </section> <!-- End of define Unvalidated Phase -->

    <section anchor="val-phase" title="Validating Phase">
        <t>The Validating Phase checks that packets
        sent in the Unvalidated Phase were received without inducing congestion.
        The CWND remains unvalidated and the sender typically remains in this phase for one RTT.
         (Note: When the full jump_cwnd is not
        fully utilised, the CWND will be reset to the flight_size to match the smaller capacity being validated.)
        </t>
        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Validating Phase (Limiting CWND on entry):
            On entry to the Validating Phase, the CWND is set to the flight_size.</t>
		
            <t>Validating Phase (Updating CWND): The CWND is updated using the
            normal rules for the current congestion controller, this typically
            allows CWND to be increased for each ACK recieved that
            indicates
            a packet has been successfully sent across the path.</t>
            
            <t>Validating Phase (Receiving acknowledgements for unvalidated packets):
                The variable PipeSize if increased upon each
                acknowledgment that indicates a packet has been
                successfuly sent over the path. This records
                the validated PipeSize in bytes.</t>

            <t>Validating Phase (Congestion indication):
            If a sender determines that congestion was experienced
            (e.g., packet loss or ECN-CE marking), Careful Resume
            enters the Safe Retreat Phase.</t>
            
            <t>Validating Phase (Receiving acknowledgement for all unvalidated packets):
	    The sender enters the Normal Phase when an acknowledgement is
            received for the last packet number (or higher)
            that was sent in the Unvalidated Phase.</t>
        </list></t> <!-- End of list of actions -->
    </section> <!-- End of define Validating Phase -->
    
    <section anchor="ret-phase" title="Safe Retreat Phase">
        
        <t>This phase is entered when the first loss/ECN-CE marking is 
	detected is detected for unvalidated packets,
        and drains the path of other unvalidated packets.
        (This trigger is the same as used by a QUIC sender to transition
        from Slow Start to Recovery <xref target="RFC9002"></xref> .)</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Safe Retreat Phase (Removing saved information): The set of saved CC parameters for
            the path are deleted, to prevent these
            from being used again by other flows.</t>
		
            <t>Safe Retreat Phase (Re-initializing CC): On entry,
            the CWND MUST be reduced to
            no more than the (PipeSize/2).
            This avoids persistent starvation by allowing capacity for other flows to regain
            their share of the total capacity.</t>
            
            <t>Safe Retreat Phase (QUIC recovery): When the CWND is reduced,
            a QUIC sender can immediately send a single packet prior to the reduction
            <xref target="RFC9002"></xref>.
            (This speeds up loss
            recovery if the data in the lost packet is retransmitted and is
            similar to TCP as described in Section 5 of <xref target="RFC6675"></xref>.)</t>

            <t>Safe Retreat Phase (Increasing CWND):
            The CWND MUST NOT be increased in this Phase.</t>

	    <t>Safe Retreat Phase (Tracking PipeSize):
            The sender continues to update
            the PipeSize after processing each ACK.
            This value is used to
            reset the ssthresh when leaving this phase, it does
            not modify CWND.</t>
				
            <t>Safe Retreat Phase (Receiving acknowledgement for all unvalidated packets):
	    The sender enters Normal Phase
            when the last packet (or later) sent during the
            Unvalidated Phase has been acknowledged. The sender
            MUST set the ssthresh to no morethan the PipeSize.</t>
        </list></t>
     
        <t>Implementation requirements are provided in
        <xref target="req-retreat"></xref>.</t>

        <section anchor="loss" title="Loss Recovery after entering Safe Retreat">

        <t>Unacknowledged packets that were sent in the Unvalidated Phase
        can be lost when there is congestion.
        Loss recovery commences using the reduced CWND
        that was set on entry to the Safe Retreat Phase.
		
        <!--The way CWND is updated
                is different from the design for TCP <xref target="RFC5681"></xref>
                and from QUIC Loss Detection and Congestion Control <xref target="RFC9002"></xref>.-->
            </t>

            <t><list>
                 <t>NOTE: A TCP or SCTP sender is required to retransmit
                 all lost data.
                 For QUIC and DCCP, the need for loss recovery
                 depends on the sender policy for retransmission.</t>
                
                 <t>NOTE: During loss recovery, a receiver can cumulatively acknowledge
                 data that was previously sent in the Unvalidated Phase in addition
                 to acknowledging successful retransmission of data.
                 <xref target="RFC3465"></xref> describes how to appropriately
                 account for such acknowledgments.</t>
            
                <t>NOTE: On entry to the Safe Retreat Phase, the CWND can be
                significantly reduced, when there was multiple loss,
                recovery of all lost data could require multiple RTTs to complete.</t>
            </list></t>

            <t>The sender leaves the Safe Retreat Phase when
                the last packet number (or higher) sent in the
                Unvalidated Phase is acknowledged.
                If the last packet number is not cumulatively acknowledged, then
            additional packets might need to be retransmitted.</t>

        </section>     <!-- End of subsection Safe Retreat Phase: loss recovery -->
    </section> <!-- End of Safe Retreat Phase -->

    <section anchor="Normal_Phase" title="Normal Phase">

        <t>In the Normal Phase, the sender transitions to using 
            the normal CC method (e.g., in congestion avoidance if CWND is more than ssthresh).
            (Note that when the sender did not use the entire jump_cwnd the CWND was reduced
	     on entering the Validating Phase.</t>
        <t>Implementation requirements are provided in <xref target="req-normal"></xref>.</t>

    </section> <!-- End of define "Normal Phase:" -->
        
    <section title="RTO Expiry while using Careful Resume">
        <t>A sender that experiences a Retransmission Time Out (RTO) expiry
        ceases to use Careful Resume.
        The sender continues enters the Normal Phase.
        
        <list>
             <t>NOTE: As in loss recovery, data sent in the
             Unvalidated Phase could be later acknowledged after an RTO event
             (see <xref target="loss"></xref>).</t>
        </list></t>
    </section> <!-- End of section: RTO Expiry -->
</section>

<!-- ****************************************************************************************** -->
<!--- Here we provide guidance and requirements on implementation     -->
    
<section title="Congestion Control Guidelines and Requirements">

    <t>This section provides guidance for implementation and use.</t>

    <section anchor="req-observe" title="Determining the Current Path Capacity in the Observe Phase">
            
        <t>There are various approaches to measuring the capacity used by a connection.
        Congestion controllers, such as CUBIC or Reno, can estimate the
        capacity by utilizing the
        CWND or flight_size. A different approach could
        estimate the same parameters for a rate-based congestion
        controller, such as BBR <xref target="I-D.cardwell-iccrg-bbr-congestion-control"></xref>,
        or by observing the rate at which data is acknowledged by the remote endpoint.</t>

        <t>Implementations are expected to include a
        LifeTime parameter in the CC parameters that can be used to remove old CC parameters
        when no longer needed, or the CC parameters are out of date.</t>

        <t> <list style="symbols">
            <!-- Avoid unhelpful use of the Careful Resume for small CWNDs.-->

            <t>Observe Phase: There are cases where the current CWND
            does not reflect the path capacity. At the end of slow
            start, the CWND can be significantly larger than
            needed to fully utilize the path (i.e., a CWND
            overshoot). It is inappropriate to use an
            overshoot in the CWND as a basis for estimating the
            capacity. In most cases, the CWND will converge to a stable
            value after several more RTTs.
            One mitigation could be to set the
            saved_cwnd based on
            the flight_size, or an averaged CWND.</t>
		
            <t>Observe Phase (Rate-limited sender): When the sender
            is rate-limited, or in an RTT following a burst of
            transmission, a sender typically transmits
            much less data than allowed. Such observations could to be discounted when
            estimating the saved_cwnd (e.g., when a previous
            observation recorded a higher value.)</t>
        </list></t>
    </section> <!-- Observe Phase  (measuring) -->

    <section anchor="req-recon"  title="Confirming the Path in the Reconnaissance Phase">	    
        <t> The CC is not modified during the Reconnaissance Phase.
        A sender therefore needs to limit the initial data,
        sent in the first RTT of transmitted data,
        to not more than the IW <xref target="RFC9000"></xref>.
        This transmission using the IW is
        assumed to be a safe starting point for any path to avoid
        adding excessive load to a potentially congested path.
        (When used in a controlled
        network, additional information about local path characteristics
        could be known, which might be used to configure a non-standard
        IW.)</t>

        <t>The method does not permit multiple concurrent reuse of
        the saved CC parameters. When multiple new concurrent connections
        are made to a server, each can have a valid endpoint_token,
        but the saved_cwnd can only be used for one new connection.
        This is designed to prevent a sender from performing multiple jumps in the cwnd,
        each individually based on the same saved_cwnd, and hence creating an
        excessive aggregate load at the bottleneck.</t>

        <t>The method used to prevent re-use of the saved CC parameters
        will depend on the design of the server that is being used
        (e.g., if all connections from a given client IP arrive at the
        same server process, then the server process could use a hash table).
        A distributed system might be required when using some types of load
        balancing, to ensure this invariant when the load balancing hashes
        connections by 4-tuple and hence multiple connections from the same
        client device are served by different server processes.</t>

	<t>In the Reconnaissance Phase a sender initiates a connection
        and starts sending initial data.
        This measures the current minimum RTT.
	If a decision is made to use Careful Resume, this is used to confirm the path.</t>

        <section anchor="sec-confirm-rtt" title="Confirming the RTT">
            <t>Path characteristics can change over time for many reasons,
            resulting in the previously observed CC parameters
            becoming irrelevant. The sender therefore compares the 
            saved_RTT with each of a
                series of measured RTT samples.</t>
                
             <t>If the current RTT sample is less than a half of the
             saved_RTT, this is regarded as too small, and is an indicator of a path change.
             (This factor of two arises, because the rate should not exceed the observed rate when
             the saved_cwnd was measured, because the jump_cwnd is calculated as half the
             measured saved_cwnd.)</t>
		
             <t>A current RTT larger than that at the time the saved_cwnd was measured results
             in a proportionally lower resumed rate, because the transmission using the CR method
             is paced based on the current RTT (i.e., the larger RTT samples reduces the paced
	     sending rate in the Unvalidated Phase - and hence is still safe).</t>
	     <t>Also note that when the RTT is incorrectly measured as larger
	     than the actual path RTT, the sender will receive an acknowledgment for an
             unvalidated packet before it might have completed the Unvalidated Phase, this
	     acknowledgment resets the CWND to reflect the flight_size, and the sender enters
	     the Validating Phase.</t>

	     <t>an RTT sample more than ten times the
             saved_RTT is indicative of a path change.
	     (The value of ten was chosen to accommodate both increases in latency from buffering
	     on a path, and any variation between RTT samples). </t>

            <t>A sender in Reconnaissance Phase reverts to the Normal Phase if congestion is detected.
            Some transport protocols implement methods that infer potential congestion
            from an increase in the RTT.
            In the Reconnaissance Phase, this indication occurs earlier than congestion
            which is reported by
            loss or by ECN marking. Designs need to consider if this is
            a suitable trigger to revert to the Normal Phase.</t>
        </section> <!-- End of Reconnaissance:Confirming the Path -->
    </section> <!-- End of Reconnaissance(req-recon) -->

    <section anchor="req-unvalid" title="Safety Requirements for the Unvalidated Phase">
        <t> This section defines the safety requirements
        for using saved CC parameters to tentatively update the CWND.
        These safety requirements mitigate the risk of
        adding excessive congestion to an already congested path.</t>

        <t> <list style="symbols">
            <t>Unvalidated Phase (Jump): A connection must not directly use the previously
                saved_cwnd to directly initialize a new flow causing it to resume sending at the same
                rate. The jump_cwnd must be no more than half the previously saved_cwnd.</t>
        </list></t>

        <section anchor="req-lifetime" title="Lifetime of CC Parameters">

	    <t>The long-term use of the previously observed parameters is not appropriate,
	    a lifetime therefore needs to be specified during
	    which the saved CC parameters can be safely re-used.</t>
	    <t><xref target="RFC9040"></xref> provides guidance on the implementation of
	    TCP Control Block Interdependence, but does not specify how long a saved
	    parameter can safely be reused.</t>
	    
	    <t><xref target="RFC7661"></xref> specifies a method for managing an
	    unvalidated CWND. This states:
	    "After a fixed period of time (the non-validated period (NVP)), the sender
	    adjusts the cwnd (Section 4.4.3). The NVP SHOULD NOT exceed five minutes."
	    Section 5 of <xref target="RFC7661"></xref> discusses the rationale for
	    choosing that period.
	    However, RFC 7661 targets rate-limited connections using normal
	    CC. The method described in the present specification includes additional
	    mechanisms to avoid and mitigate the effects of overshoot, and therefore
	    this can be used to justify a longer lifetime of the saved_cwnd using
	    the Careful Resume method.</t>
		
            <t>{XXX-Editor NOTE: A future revision of this document could specify a maximum time that
            CC Parameters can be cached - Ought this to me minutes, hours, days?}</t>
        </section> <!-- End of Reconnaissance:Liftetime of Params -->
            
        <section anchor="req-pace" title="Pacing in the Unvalidated Phase">
        
            <t> The sender must avoid sending a burst of packets greater than IW as a result of a
            step-increase in the CWND. (This is consistent with <xref target="RFC8085"></xref>,
            <xref target="RFC9000"></xref>).
           

            Pacing sent packets as a function of
            the current RTT, rather than the saved_RTT,
            provides an additional safety during the
            Unvalidated Phase.
            Other sender mitigations have also been suggested to
            avoid line-rate bursts (e.g., <xref target="I-D.hughes-restart"></xref>).</t>
            
            <t>Pacing places a limitation on the minimum acceptable current_RTT
                to avoid sending at a rate higher than was previously observed.</t>

            <t>The following example provides a relevant pacing rhythm using the RTT and the
            saved_cwnd. The Inter-packet Transmission Time (ITT) is determined
            by using the current Maximum Message Size (MMS),
            the saved_cwnd and the RTT. A safety
            margin can avoid sending more than a recommended maximum
            (max_jump):
            <list>
                <t>jump_cwnd = min(max_jump,saved_cwnd/2)</t>
                <t>ITT = (current_RTT x MMS)/jump_cwnd</t>
            </list></t>
            <t>This follows the idea presented in <xref target="RFC4782"></xref>,
            <xref target="I-D.irtf-iccrg-sallantin-initial-spreading"></xref> and
            <xref target="CONEXT15"></xref>.</t>
        </section> <!-- Unvalidated Phase: Pacing  -->
        
        <section title="Exit from the Unvalidated Phase because of Variable Network Conditions">
            <t><list style="symbols">
                <t>Careful Resume has been designed to be robust to
            changes in network conditions
            due to variations in the forwarding path, such as reconfiguration of
            equipment, or changes in the link conditions. This is mitigated
            by path confirmation.</t>

                <t>Careful Resume has been designed to be robust to changes
                in network traffic, including the
                arrival of new flows that compete for capacity at a shared bottleneck.
                This is mitigated by jumping to no more than a half of
                the saved_cwnd and by using pacing.</t>
		    
                <t>Careful Resume has been designed to prevent unduly suppressing flows
                that used the capacity since the available capacity was measured. This is further
                mitigated by bounding the duration of the Unvalidated Phase (and the following
                Validating Phase).</t>

            </list></t>
        </section> <!--  Unvalidated Phase:  Subsection: Network Conditions -->

    </section> <!-- Unvalidated Phase -->

    <section anchor="req-val" title="Safety Requirements for the Validating Phase">
        <t>When a sender completes the Unvalidated Phase, either by sending a jump_cwnd of data
        or after one RTT, it ceases to use the unvalidated CWND. That is, CWND is reset
        to the flight_size, and the sender awaits reception of the acknowledgments to validate the
        use of this capacity. New packets are sent when previously
        sent data is newly acknowledged. The purpose is to trigger a
        safe retreat in the case when the capacity is not validated.</t>
        <t>Note that the CWND is increased during the Validating Phase,
            based on received ACKs. This allows new data to be sent,
            but this does not have any final impact on the CWND
            if congestion is detected.</t>
     </section> <!-- Validating Phase -->

    <section anchor="req-retreat" title="Safety Requirements for the Safe Retreat Phase">
         <t>This section defines the safety requirements
         after congestion has been detected during the Unvalidated Phase.</t>

	<t>The Safe Retreat Phse sets a safe CWND value to drain unvalidated packets
	from the path when a packet loss is detected or acknowledgments indicate sent
        packets were ECN CE-marked.</t>

         <t>The Safe Retreat reaction differs from a traditional
         reaction to detected congestion, because
         the jump_cwnd can result in a significantly higher rate than would be allowed by the
         slow-start mechanism. This could aggressively feed a congested bottleneck,
         resulting in overshoot where a disproportionate number of packets
         from existing flows are displaced from
         the buffer at the congested bottleneck.
         For this reason, a sender needs to react to detected congestion by
         reducing CWND significantly
         below the saved_cwnd.</t>
	 
        <t>Note: Proportional Rate Reduction (PRR) <xref target="RFC6937"></xref>
        assumes that it is safe to reduce
        the rate gradually when in congestion avoidance.
        PRR is therefore not appropriate
        when there might be significant overshoot in the use of the capacity, which can
        be the case when the Safe Retreat Phase is entered.</t>

        <t>Acknowledgements
         for unvalidated packets are tracked to
         measure the maximum capacity, called the PipeSize
         (The first unvalidated packet can be determined by
         recording the sequence number
         of the first packet sent in this phase.)
         This PipSize is not a safe measure of the currently
         available share of the capacity whenever
         there was also a significant overshoot at the bottleneck,
          but may be used to reset ssthresh.</t>

    </section><!-- End of Safety Requirements for the Safe Retreat Phase -->

    <section anchor="req-normal" title="Returning to Normal Congestion Control">
        <t>After using Careful Resume, the CC controller returns to the Normal Phase.
        The implementation details for different transports depend on the
        design of the transport.</t>

        <!---<list>
            <t>For NewReno and CUBIC, it is recommended to exit slow-start
            and enter the congestion avoidance phase of the CC method.</t>

            <t>For BBR CC, it is recommended to enter the "probe bandwidth"
            state.</t>
        </list></t>-->
	<t>In the Normal Phase, a sender can enter the Observation Phase to perform
	observation of the path.</t>
        <t>{XXX-Editor note: A future revision should discuss updating
        the saved parameters, whether used or not, after reaching normal operation for use
        the next time even if that update is to just refresh the expiration time.}</t>
    </section><!-- End of Normal Phase -->
    <section anchor="flow-control" title="Limitations from Transport Protocols">

        <t>A sender is limited by any rate-limitation of the transport
        protocol that is used.
        <list>

            <t>For QUIC this includes flow control mechanisms or preventing amplification
            attacks. In particular, a QUIC receiver might need to issue proactive
            MAX_DATA frames to increase the flow control limits of a connection
            that is started when using Careful Resume to gain the expected benefit.</t>

            <t>A TCP sender is limited by the receiver window (rwnd).
            Unless configured at a receiver, the rwnd constrains the rate
            of increase for a connection and reduces the benefit of Careful Resume.</t>
        </list></t>

    </section>     <!-- End of flow control, etc -->

</section> <!--  End of Guidelines -->

<section anchor="sec-QLOG" title="QLOG support for QUIC">
	<t> {XXX-Editor note: This section to be completed XXX}</t>
    <t>This section provides definitions that enable the
	Careful Resume method
	to generate qlog events when using QUIC.
	It introduces an event to report the current phase of a sender, 
	and the associated description.</t>
	
	<t>The event and data structure definitions in this section are
	expressed in the Concise Data Definition Language (CDDL)
	<xref target="RFC8610"></xref> and its
	extensions described in <xref target="I-D.ietf-quic-qlog-quic-events"></xref>.</t>
	
	<section title="cr_phase Event">
		<!--<name>cr_phase</name>-->
		<t>Importance: Extra</t>

		<t>When the CC algorithm changes the Careful Resume Phase 
		described in <xref target="sec-phase"></xref> of this specification.</t>
       		 <t>Definition:</t>

		<figure anchor="qlog-def">
	         <!--- 	<name>cr_phase</name> -->
<sourcecode type="cddl"><![CDATA[
XX Fix me as CDDL XX
<!-- CrState::OBSERVE => { 0 }
CrState::RECON => { 1 }
CrState::UNVAL => { 2 }
CrState::VALIDATE => { 3 }
CrState::NORMAL => { 4 }
CrState::RETREAT => { 100 } -->

]]></sourcecode>
		</figure>
   
	</section> 
</section> <!--  End of Qlog -->

<section anchor="sec-acknowledgments" title="Acknowledgments">
        <t>The authors would like to thank John Border, Gabriel Montenegro, Patrick McManus,
        Ian Swett, Igor Lubashev, Robin Marx, Roland Bless, Franklin Simo, Kazuho Oku, Tong,
        Ana Custura, and Neal Cardwell for
        their fruitful comments on earlier versions of this document.</t>
        <t>The authors would like to particularly thank Tom Jones for co-authoring
        several previous versions of this document. Ana Custura developed the qlog support.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sec-IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
        <t>No current parameters are required to be registered by IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sec-security" title="Security Considerations">
        <t>This document does not exhibit specific security considerations.
        Security considerations for the
        interactions with the receiver are discussed in <xref
        target="I-D.kuhn-quic-bdpframe-extension"></xref>.</t>
    </section> <!-- Sec Considerations -->
        
</middle>

  <!--  BACK MATTER -->

  <back>
    <!-- References split into informative and normative -->

    <!-- There are 2 ways to insert reference entries from the citation libraries:
1. define an ENTITY at the top, and use "ampersand character"RFC2629; here (as shown)
2. simply use a PI "less than character"?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?> here
(for I-Ds: include="reference.I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis.xml")
Both are cited textually in the same manner: by using xref elements.
If you use the PI option, xml2rfc will, by default, try to find included files in the same
directory as the including file. You can also define the XML_LIBRARY environment variable
with a value containing a set of directories to search.  These can be either in the local
filing system or remote ones accessed by http (http://domain/dir/... ).-->

    <references title="Normative References">
    
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>

      <!-- <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6349.xml"?> -->

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8085.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8174.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8801.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.9000.xml"?>

      <!-- <?rfc include="reference.RFC.9001.xml"?> -->

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8610.xml"?>

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
	  <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-quic-qlog-quic-events.xml"?>
          <?rfc include="reference.I-D.irtf-iccrg-sallantin-initial-spreading.xml"?>
    <?rfc include="reference.I-D.cardwell-iccrg-bbr-congestion-control.xml"?>
          <?rfc include="reference.I-D.kuhn-quic-bdpframe-extension.xml"?>
          <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3465.xml"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4782.xml"?>
	    <!-- <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5681.xml"?> -->
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5783.xml"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6675.xml"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6937.xml"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7661.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8867.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.9002.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.9040.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.9406.xml"?>

    <!--- A manual format reference to over-ride broken ID Archive reference (missing authors, noted by J.Touch). -->
    <reference anchor="I-D.hughes-restart" target="https://www.ietf.org/archive/id/draft-hughes-restart-00.txt">
       <front>
           <title>Issues in TCP Slow-Start Restart After Idle</title>
           <author initials="A" surname="Hughes" fullname="Amy S Hughes">
               <organization>ISI</organization>
           </author>
           <author initials="J" surname="Touch" fullname="Joe Touch">
               <organization>ISI</organization>
            </author>
            <author initials="J" surname="Heidemann" fullname="John Heidemann">
               <organization>ISI</organization>
            </author>
            <date month="December" year="2001" />
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="Work in Progress, Internet-Draft," value="draft-hughes-restart-00" />
        <refcontent></refcontent>
   </reference>
	    
      <reference anchor="MAPRG111">
        <front>
          <title>Feedback from using QUIC's 0-RTT-BDP extension over SATCOM
          public access</title>

          <author initials="N" surname="Kuhn"></author>

          <author initials="E" surname="Stephan"></author>

          <author initials="G" surname="Fairhurst"></author>

          <author initials="T" surname="Jones"></author>

          <author initials="C" surname="Huitema"></author>

          <date year="2022" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="IETF 111 - MAPRG meeting" value="" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="IJSCN">
        <front>
          <title>Google QUIC performance over a public SATCOM access</title>

          <author initials="L" surname="Thomas"></author>

          <author initials="E" surname="Dubois"></author>

          <author initials="N" surname="Kuhn"></author>

          <author initials="E" surname="Lochin"></author>

          <date year="2019" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="International Journal of Satellite Communications and Networking"
                    value="10.1002/sat.1301" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="CONEXT15">
        <front>
          <title>Halfback: Running Short Flows Quickly and Safely</title>

          <author initials="Q" surname="Li"></author>

          <author initials="M" surname="Dong"></author>

          <author initials="P B" surname="Godfrey"></author>

          <date year="2015" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="ACM CoNEXT" value="" />
      </reference>
    </references>

<section anchor="Examples" title="Notes on the Careful Resume Phases">

    <t> The table below is provided to illustrate the operation of Careful Resume. 
    This table is informative, please refer to the body of the document 
    for the normative specification. The description is based on a Normal 
    CC using Reno or Cubic.</t>

 <t>
 <artwork align="left" name="table" type="" alt=""><![CDATA[
+------+---------+---------+------------+-----------+------------+
|Phase |Normal   |Recon.   |Unvalidated |Validating |Safe Retreat|
+------+---------+---------+------------+-----------+------------+
|      |Observe  |Confirm  |Send faster |Validate   |Drain path; |
|      |CC params|path     |using saved |new CWND   |Update PS   |
|      |         |         |            |Update PS  |            |
+------+---------+---------+------------+-----------+------------+
|On    |    -    |CWND=IW  |PS=CWND;    |CWND=FS    |CWND=(PS/2) |
|entry:|         |         |CWND        |           |            |
|      |         |         |=jump_cwnd  |           |            |
+------+---------+---------+------------+-----------+------------+
|CWND: |When in  |CWND     |CWND is not |CWND can   |CWND is not |
|      |observe, |increases|increased   |increase   |increased   |
|      |measure  |using SS |            |using SS   |            |
|      |sav_cwnd |         |            |           |            |
+------+---------+---------+------------+-----------+------------+
|PS:   |    -    |    -    |              PS+=ACked              |
+------+---------+---------+------------+-----------+------------+
|RTT:  |Measure  |Measure  |      -     |     -     |      -     |
|      |saved_rtt|current  |            |           |            |
|      |         |_rtt     |            |           |            |
+------+---------+---------+------------+-----------+------------+
|If    |Normal   |Normal   |          Enter         |      -     |
|loss  |CC method|CC method|          Safe          |            |
|or    |         |CR is not|          Retreat       |            |
|ECNCE:|         |allowed  |                        |            |
+------+---------+---------+------------+-----------+------------+
|Next  |Observe  |If (     |If( >1 RTT  |If (last   |If (last    |
|Phase:|(as      |FS=CWND  |has passed  |unvalidated|unvalidated |
|      |needed)  |and CR   |or FS=CWND  |packet is  |packet is   |
|      |         |confirmed|or first    |ACKed)     |ACKed},     |
|      |         |), enter |unvalidated |enter      |ssthresh=PS |
|      |         |Unvalid- |packet is   |Normal     |and then    |
|      |         |ing else |ACKed),     |           |enter       |
|      |         |enter    |enter       |           |Normal      |
|      |         |Normal   |Validating  |           |            |
+------+---------+---------+------------+-----------+------------+
]]></artwork>
</t>

<t>Notes:
SS = slow start FS= flight_size; PS = PipeSize.</t>

   <t>The remaining subsections provide informative examples of use.</t>

<t>XXXX ACTIONS
Add PipeSize text
SWND is always based on PS - but explain the meaning of PS=CWND on ENTRY XXX</t>

    <section anchor="Examples-no loss" title="Example with No Loss">
	<t>In the first example of using the Careful Resume method, 
	the sender starts by sending IW (10) packets in the Reconnaissance Phase, 
	and then continues in a subsequent RTT to send more packets until the sender 
	becomes CWND-limited (i.e., flight_size = CWND).</t>
	    
	<t>The sender then
	confirms the RTT and other conditions for using Careful Resume.
	In this example, this is confirmed when the sender has 29 packets in flight.
	The sender enters the Unvalidated Phase.
	This confirmation could have happened earlier if data was available to send. The
	sender initialises the PipeSize to to the CWND (the same as the flight_size, i.e., 29 packets)
	and sets the CWND to 150 packets (based upon a previously
	observed saved_cwnd of 300 packets).</t>
	    
	<t>It now sends 121 unvalidated packets. This is the unused portion of the CWND.
	Each time a packet is sent, the sender checks whether 1 RTT has passed since entering the
	Unvalidated Phase (otherwise, the Validating Phase is entered). This check triggers only
	for cases where the sender is rate-limited, see the following example.</t>

	<t>The PipeSize will increase after each ACK is received.</t>
	
	<t>When the first unvalidated packet is acknowledged (packet number 30) the sender
	enters the Validating Phase. This transition would also occur if the flight_size increases to equal CWND.
	During this phase, the CWND can be increased for each ACK for an unvalidated packet, because
	this indicates that the packet was indeed validated.</t>

	<t>When an ACK is received for the last packet sent in the Unvalidated Phase,
	the sender completes using Careful Resume. It enters the Normal Phase. If CWND is less than ssthresh,
	a Reno or Cubic sender in the Normal Phase is permitted to use slow start to grow the CWND towards
	the ssthresh, and will then enter congestion avoidance.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Examples-dl" title="Example with No Loss, Rate-Limited">
    	<t>A rate-limited sender will not fully utilize the available CWND when using Careful Resume,
	and CWND is therefore reset on entry to the Validating Phase, as described below.</t>

	<t>The sender in this example starts by sending IW packets (10) in the Reconnaissance Phase,
	and sends as described in the first example, transitioning to the Unvalidated Phase.
	This sets the CWND to 150 packets, and the PipeSize is set to the flight_size (i.e., 29 packets).</t>
		
	<t>The sender then becomes rate-limited because it only sends 50 unvalidated packets.</t>
	
	<t> After ~1 RTT (detected by using local timestamps or by receiving an ACK for the first
	unvalidated packet), the sender will still not have fully used the CWND. It then enters 
	the Validating Phase and resets the CWND to the current flight_size, (i.e., 50 packets).
	During this phase, the CWND can be increased for each ACK that validates reception of a packet.
	The PipeSize also increases with each ACK received, to reflect the discovered capacity.</t>

	<t>When an ACK is received for the last packet sent in the Unvalidated Phase,
	the sender has completed using Careful Resume. It enters the Normal Phase. If CWND is less than ssthresh,
	a Reno or Cubic sender in the Normal Phase is permitted to use slow start to grow the CWND towards
	the ssthresh, and will then enter congestion avoidance.</t>
    </section>
	    
    <section anchor="Examples-loss-recon" title="Example with Loss detected in the Reconnaissance Phase">
	<t>When a packet is lost in the Reconnaissance Phase, the sender enters the Normal Phase
	and recovers this using normal method. There is no change to the CC method, because
	the sender has discovered a potential capacity limit and is not
	allowed to use Careful Resume.</t>
     </section>
	
     <section anchor="Examples-loss-unval" title="Example with Loss detected in the Validating Phase">
	<t>As in the first Example the sender enters the Unvalidated Phase it sets the CWND to 150 packets
	with the PipeSize initialized to the flight_size (i.e., 29 packets).</t>

	<t>The sender now sends 121 unvalidated packets (the remaining unused CWND).
	This example considers the case when one of the unvalidated packet is lost, which
	we choose to be packet 64 (the 35th packet in the Unvalidated Phase).</t>

	<t>Acknowledgements confirm the first 34 unvalidated packets are received without loss.
	The PipeSize at this point is equal to 29 + 34 = 63 packets.</t>
		
	<t>The loss is then detected (by receiving three ACKs that do not cover packet number 35),
	the sender then enters the Safe Retreat Phase because the window was not validated.
	The PipeSize at this point is equal to 29 + 34 = 66 packets. Assuming IW=10.
	The CWND is reset to Max(10,ps/2) = Max(10,66/2) = 33 packets.
	This CWND is used during the Safe Retreat Phase, because congestion was detected and the
	sender still does not know if the remaining unvalidated packets will be
	successfully acknowledged. A conservative CWND calculation ensures the sender drains
	the path after this potentially severe congestion event.
	There is no further increase in CWND in this phase.</t>

	<t>The sender continues to receives ACKs for the remaining  86 (121-35) unvalidated packets
	(recall that the 35th unvalidated packet was lost and had packet number 29+35=64).
	The PipeSize continues to further increase as each ACK acknowledges new data, because this tracks the
	size of the pipe discovered by the unvalidated packets.
	Although this cannot be used to safety initialise CWND (because was measured when the sender
	aggressively created overload), the estimated PipeSize
	(which, in this case, is 121-1 = 120 packets) can be used to set the ssthresh on exit
	from Safe Retreat, since it indicates an upper limit to the current capacity.</t>

	<t>At the point where all packets sent in the Unvalidated Phase have been either acknowledged
	or declared lost, the sender enters the Normal Phase, but first updates ssthresh.
	Because CWND will now now less than ssthresh, a sender in the Normal Phase is permitted to use 
	slow start to grow the CWND towards the ssthresh, after which it will enter congestion avoidance.</t>
     </section>
		    
</section> <!--- worked examples-->

<section anchor="endpoint_token" title="Appendix: An Endpoint Token">

    <t>
    This annex proposes an Endpoint Token to allow a sender to identify its own
            view of the network path that it is using. In <xref target="I-D.kuhn-quic-bdpframe-extension"></xref>
        this Endpoint Token could be shared and used as an
    opaque path identifier to other parties and the sender can verify if
    this is one of its current paths.
    </t>

    <section title="Creating an Endpoint Token">
            <t>
            When computing the Endpoint Token, the sender includes information to identify
            the path on which it sends, for example, this:
            <list style="symbols">
            <t>
            needs to include a unique identifier for itself (e.g., a globally
            assigned address/prefix; or randomly chosen value such as a nonce);
            </t>
            <t>
            needs to include an identifier for the destination (e.g., a
            destination IP address or name);
            </t>
            <t>
            needs to include an interface identifier (e.g., an index value or a MAC address to associate the
            endpoint with the interface on which the path starts);
            </t>
            <t>
            could include other information such as the DSCP, ports, flow
            label, etc (recognising that this additional information might improve the path
            differentiation, but that this can reduce the re-usability of the
            token);
            </t>
            <t>
            this could include any other information the sender chooses to
            include, and potentially including PvD information <xref target="RFC8801"></xref> or
            information relating to its public-facing IP address;
            </t>
            
       </list></t>

        <t>
        When creating an Endpoint Token, the sender has to ensure the following:
        <list style="numbers">
            <t>To reduce the likelihood of misuse of the Endpoint Token, the value
            ought to be encoded in a way that hides the component information
            from the recipient and any eavesdropper on the path (this could already protected by methods
            such as TLS).</t>
            
            <t>The sender can recalculate the Endpoint Token to validate a
            previously issued token; and can be
            included in the computed integrity check for any path
            information it provides.</t>
            <t> The Endpoint Token is designed so that if shared, it prevents another party from deriving
            private data from the token, or to use the token to perform
            unwanted likability with other information. Therefore,
            the Endpoint Token MUST necessarily be different when used to identify
            paths using different interfaces.</t>
       </list> </t>
    </section>

 </section> <!-- End of An Endpoint Token -->
      
<section anchor="rev" title="Appendix: Revision details">
    <t>Previous individual submissions were discussed in TSVWG and QUIC.
    <list>
        <t>WG -00 included clarifications and restructuring to form the 1st WG draft.</t>
        <t>WG -01 included review comments and suggestions from John Border,
        and follows the setting of the TSVWG milestone
        with an intended status of "Proposed Standard".</t>
        <t>WG -02 includes steps to complete the spec. In particular, consideration of rate-limited
        senders; selection of reasoned parameters; specification of the Safe Retreat Phase; and
            improvements to the consistency throughout. Added the Validating Phase.</t>
        <t>WG -03, explain entry to Validating Phase, editorial tidy.</t>
        <t>WG -04, update based on review comments from Kazuho Oku.</t>
        <t>WG-05, update based on review comments from Neal Cardwell. WG feedback from IETF-118.
        Reviewed the requirements v. guidelines; clarified that CC is not changed in recon., but
        the recon. info is used to steer the next phase; clarified saved_cwnd can be computed
        from ACK rate; use jump once; that real server platforms are complex.
	Clarified lifetime for saved CC params. Incorporates comments from Tong.</t>
	<t>WG-06, SR updated following Hackathon comments from Kazuho Oku, and rework of use of PipeSize.
	Added an informative summary of actions, on suggestion by Tong. Added examples based on text by Ana Custura. </t>
	<t>WG-07, Use "rate-limited" uniformally instead of application and data limited.</t>

    </list></t>
</section> <!-- End of Revisions -->

</back>
</rfc>
